James Gross NLRB Files /4057
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
James Gross NLRB Files
1933-1977
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Gross, James
/4057
15 cubic feet
15 linear ft.
Records (documents).
3079878
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, February 02, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, September 23, 2016
Biographical / Historical
Professor Gross teaches Labor Law, Labor Arbitration, and a course entitled Values, Rights and Justice in Economics, Law, and Industrial Relations. He received his B.S. from LaSalle College, M.A. from Temple University, and Ph.D. from University of Wisconsin.
Professor Gross is a member of National Academy of Arbitrators and on the labor arbitration panels of the American Arbitration Association, Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service and New York State Public Employment Relations Board, as well as being a panelist named in several contracts.[www.ilr.cornell.edu/directory/jag28/biography.htm]
Biographical / Historical
NLRB 1935-2010
The National Labor Relations Board is proud of its 75-year history of enforcing the National Labor Relations Act, the primary law governing relations between employers and employees in the private sector. On July 5, 1935, President Franklin Roosevelt signed the Act into law, stating that the law sought to achieve "common justice and economic advance." Starting in the Great Depression and continuing through World War II and the economic growth and challenges that followed, the NLRB has worked to guarantee the rights of employees to bargain collectively, if they choose to do so.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4057: James Gross NLRB Files /4057 P: James Gross NLRB Photographs /4079: James Gross Additional Files /4124: James Gross Papers, Additional NLRB Research Files /4166: James Gross Additional NLRB Research Files /4186: James Gross Additional Research Files /4190: James Gross Additional Research Files 5697: James A. Gross Arbitration Files 5959: James Gross Additional Arbitration Files
Arrangement
Series I. NATIONAL LABOR BOARD, 1933-1934 (JUNE)
Sub-Series A. REGIONAL LABOR MEDIATION BOARD MINUTES Sub-Series B. NATIONAL LABOR BOARD RECORDS
Series II. NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD (OLD) 1934-1935 (JULY)
Sub-Series A. NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD RECORDS
Series III. NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD 7/35-11/47
Sub-Series A. NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD RECORDS Sub-Series B. DIVISION OF ECONOMIC RESEARCH RECORDS 1936-1973
Series IV. RELATED COMMITTEES
Sub-Series A. LAFOLLETTE (Robert) COMMITTEE 1935-1940 Sub-Series B. DIES (Martin) COMMITTEE RECORDS 1938-1940 Sub-Series C. BURKE (Edward R.) COMMITTEE RECORDS 1939-1941 Sub-Series D. SMITH (Howard, M.) COMMITTEE RECORDS 1937-1970
Series V. MICROFILM AND INDEX
Series VI. ORAL HISTORIES - series unprocessed as of 1/6/88
Series VII. MISCELLANEOUS
Gross, James A.,1933-; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations --Faculty.
3079878
- Series I. NATIONAL LABOR BOARD, 1933-1934 (JUNE)
  - Sub-Series A. REGIONAL LABOR MEDIATION BOARD MINUTES
    - Minutes, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      12/8/33; includes William Leiserson's, (Secretary, National Labor Board - NLB) discussion of the purpose, functions, powers and jurisdiction of the Regional Labor Mediation Board. Also includes rules for deciding cases and explanations of procedures
  - Sub-Series B. NATIONAL LABOR BOARD RECORDS
    - Sub-Series 1. CORRESPONDENCE. 8/5/33-6/16/34
      - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        8/5/33-11/18/33; Letter of appointment from President Franklin Delano Roosevelt to Senator Robert F. Wagner as chairman of the National Labor Board (NLB); from Gerald Swope, (President, General Electric Co., NLB member) and Louis E. Kirstein, (General Manager, William Filene Sons Co. NLB member) to Wagner regarding the Brockton (?) Shoe Manufacturers' case, recommending representation elections; William Leiserson's discussion of the Board's role as a mediation and arbitration board (Philadelphia Bakers' case, the Tool and Die Makers' Strike in Detroit and Flint, Jameston Art Metal Co. case), recommending that the Board remain an arbitration tribunal (Berkeley Woolen Mills case); Leiserson's resignation as Secretary; from the NLB to the Brockton Central Labor Union, includes essay "Manufacturer Fighting to Keep Closed Shop"; James O'Connel's, (President, Brockton Central Labor Union) and Frank W. Gifford's (Secretary) demand that the ruling (Douglas Shoe Co.) be recinded; Campbell MacCulloch's, (Secretary, Los Angeles Regional Labor Board) inquiry about the power and authority of regional boards as well as organizational structure and procedures; from MacCulloch to Creel concerning the selection of members to the Regional Labor Board (Byron Campbell, A. Schleicher, Tibbetts, John C. Austin, W.L. Stevens), objecting to labor appointees.
      - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        12/3/33-12/22/33; Letter from Elinore Herrick (Director, New York Regional Office) in regard to action the regional board intends to take in case no. 104; from L.L. Balleisen, (Secretary, Industrial Division, Brooklyn Chamber of Commerce) to Edward C. Blum, (President, Abraham & Straus, Inc. and Regional Board Member) about case no.104; Milton Handler's (General Counsel, NLB) explanation of the functions of regional labor boards; Daniel B. Shortal's (Buffalo Regional Labor Board) request for a copy of the decision handed down in the Philadelphia Bakery Drivers case because of it's possible affect on the Hall Baking Co. and the Bakery Drivers Union no. 264 dispute; Benedict Wolf's (Executive Officer, NLB) recommendation to begin negotiations in the Stone Knitting Co. (case no. 25-25A); from G.W. Ramaker, (Secretary, Atlanta Regional Board) to Republic Steel Corp., Birmingham, Ala. in regard to a written complaint filed by employees concerning working conditions.
      - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        1/2/34-2/20/34; Letter from MacCulloch to Creel in regard to the Greyhound and Wilson Packing Co. cases and company unions; from Wolf to Charles W. Hope (Seattle Regional Labor Board) affirming majority rule is law (Willopa Harbor Mills case); Wolf's confirmation that a union is not required to submit membership lists to a company (Houde Engineering Corporation); from the Chairman (Atlanta Regional Labor Board)(?) about Board's authority to issue binding orders (Republic Steel Corporation); Executive Order no. 6550, regulating the further allocation and obligation of emergency funds; from George L. Berry (Division Administrator, NLB and President, International Pressmen's and Assistants' Union) to Walter C. Teagle (Chairman, Industrial Advisory Board and President, Standard Oil Company) in regard to Teagle's paper "Employee Representation and Collective Bargaining", and the passage of the National Industrial Recovery Act (NIRA); Wagner's demamd for a written agreement in the Pierson Manufacturing Company case; Houde Engineering Corporation's refusal to meet the United Automobile Workers Federal Labor Union (UAW) no. 18839 representatives; from the Chicago Regional Labor Board to the NLB concerning Communist controlled unions and majority rule; from Wolf to the Chicago Regional Labor Board on the representation election process, and majority rule; from Milton Handler to the Chicago Regional Labor Board in regard to collective bargaining, written agreements (Harriman Case), and union recognition; from Wagner to the Regional Labor Boards announcing members of the State Directors of the National Emergency Council and their relation to regional boards; from the Attorney General to the President about Executive Order no. 6580; from Swope to Wagner in regard to state directors' report "Public Attitude toward the NRA Program".
      - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        3/2/34-5/21/34; Memo from Frances Perkins (Secretary of Labor) to the President recommemding Leon Marshall and Clay Williams to serve as vice-chairmen of the Board; especially significant memo from Leo Wolman (National Recovery Administration - NRA) to Handler about Hall Baking Company; from Charles R. Hook (President, Rolling Mill Company) to General Hugh S. Johnson (Administrator, NRA) calling for Wagner's resignation; Wolf's discussion of elections and management's refusal to recognize the union (Houde Engineering Corporation); from Frank E. Coffee (Secretary, Atlanta Labor Board) to Jessie I. Miller (Executive Director, NLB) regarding Republic Steel and a representation election, contains a reference to Mr. Borden Burr's letter to Youngstown; detailed statement by the President to the press on employment in the automobile industry, and a discussion of Section 7a of the NIRA as well as principles of settlement; from Coffee to J.A. Lipscomb in regard to Republic Steel and the selection of members to an arbitration board (Judge Grubb); significant memo from Handler to Miller about E.G. Budd Co.; personal letter of encouragement from Edwin S. Smith (Commissioner of Labor and Industries, Commonwealth of Massachusetts) to the President; from Miller's discussion of alleged violations of Section 7a; the President's reply to Smith; from E. (?) Curtis to Coffee regarding Republic Steel and its treatment of black workers; memo turning the Houde case over to the NLB (includes election results from 3/8/34); telephone message from Draper to unknown party providing conditions under which Houde will make a settlement; report from P.A. Donoghue (Chicago Regional Labor Board) to possibly the Chicago Regional Labor Board or the NLB in regard to Guide Lamp Co., Anderson, Indiana, and an account of Ray Kelsay's (Vice-President, Metal Polishers International Union) efforts to meet with management.
      - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        6/1/34-6/16/34; Autobiographical letter from Charles Hook to Marvin H. McIntyre (Secretary to the President) in regard to Section 3 of the Wagner Bill (4pp); from Daniel C. Roper (Secretary of Commerce) to McIntyre, and attached memo describing amendments made to the Wagner Bill by businessmen; letter of legal advice and analysis from Harold M. Stevens (Assistant Attorney General) to Wagner relating to the Great Lakes Steel Corp., A. Roth & Co., and National Lock Co.; from Perkins to McIntyre about Hook's letter of 6/1/34 and the idea of "economic coercion".
      - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Undated; Memo reviewing members of the NLB, and announcing new members; 5 point Procedure appeal from Wagner to the NLB; (illegible) "Statement to be Read to the Employer" by the NLB in regard to the S. Dresners & Son Co. case, and Local no.12, United Leather Workers International Union, and a Board sponsored election
    - Sub-Series 2. REPORTS AND OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS 1934-35
      - Radio reports; General Instructions for Regional Labor Boards; summary of NLB activities, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Reports, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        National Recovery Administration (NRA) release no.2678, NLB transmits Budd case to compliance director; 4th draft of the Wagner Act by Leon Keyserling; confidential advice from William Leiserson to regional boards; 6th draft of the Wagner Act; 1st draft of the procedural section of the Wagner Bill by Charles Wyzanski (Counsel for the Dept. of Labor); NRA release no. 3414, NLB reports to the President; NRA release no. 4118, NLB issues election regulations; statement of jurisdiction and powers of the NLB and regional labor boards; preliminary report on Board's handling 7a cases; 4 part report by Emily C. Brown on elections conducted by the NLB and regional boards 8/5/33-7/9/34; NLB principles with applicable cases 8/5/33-7/9/34.
      - The Labor Disputes Act no. S.2926 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        undated
    - Sub-Series 3. CLIPPINGS AND REPRINTS 1933-36
      - Clippings, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        8/33-9/33
      - Clippings, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        10/33-12/33
      - Clippings, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Feb-34
      - Clippings, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Mar-34
      - Clippings, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        5/34-6/34
      - Clippings, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Reprints, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        1/33-6/33
      - Reprints, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        7/33-12/33
      - Reprints, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 19)
        1/34-3/34
      - Reprints, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 20)
        Apr-34
      - Reprints, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 21)
        5/34-11/34
      - Reprints, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Dec-34
      - Reprints, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 23)
        and undated
    - Sub-Series 4. CASE FILES 10/33-5/34
      - Case files, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        National Lock Company; Denver Tramway Corporation (undated and illegible); NLB and the International Union of Office Boys and Office Girls on behalf of Irving Hebling (undated); Pierson Manufacturing Company (undated, partially illegible).
- Series II. NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD (OLD) 1934-1935 (JULY)
  - Sub-Series A. NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD RECORDS
    - Sub-Series 1. MINUTES 7/14/34-6/21/35
      - Minutes, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 25)
        7/14/34-12/12/34; Roundtable discussion on regional labor board policy, discussants include Lloyd K. Garrison (Chairman, NLRB) and Dean Spencer; Board requests survey of industrial (race) relations in Southern Cotton Textile Mills and a report on problems within the Kansas City Regional Board; a report on Kugler's Restaurant case (a violation of Sec. 7a involving employee Sussman); references to the following subjects: the Burgess case, the San Francisco Regional Board split, and the Eagle Rubber Co. case (which involves "questions of discriminatory rehiring"); the Fifth Avenue Coach Co. is turned over to New York State courts; report on reorganization of regional boards; city of Detroit attorneys turn the Detroit Street Railway Case over to the NLRB; a discussion of the A. Knabb & Son case (discrimination); Philadelphia Regional Labor Board's discussion of limitations imposed by the NLB; referral of the Hughs Tool Co. case to the New Orleans Regional Labor Board (black employees' association was not represented); Board's decision to refer all cases section 7a violations to the Department of Justice; Board's decision to notify the Governments Contracts Division, N.R.A. of companies violating Section 7a; Board returns the Ft. Wayne Printing Co. case to the Indianapolis Regional Labor Board; Board's decision to decline to exercise jurisdiction over the Brewery Drivers case, and instead honor the A.F. of L.'s jurisdiction; Board defers action on uncoded industries; Board affirms that intrastate commerce cases will not be referred to the Department of Justice for enforcement.
      - Minutes, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        5/14/35-6/21/35; NLRB corrects Stanley W.(Major) Root (Regional Director, Philadelphia Regional Labor Board) in Motor Freight Express Co. case; detailed report on the conference with regional directors by Paul M. Herzog (Assistant General Counsel, NLRB), topics discussed include: the "Use of Panels under proposed Wagner Bill", office procedures, practice, hearings, records, and interstate commerce and publicity; Presidential message extending the life of the Board (7pp).
    - Sub-Series 2. CORRESPONDENCE 6/5/34-7/6/35
      - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 27)
        6/5/34-7/16/34; Letter from A.P. Lamneck M.C. to the President on the proposed Wagner Labor Disputes Bill; from Perkins, Wagner, Donald Richberg and Charles Wyzanski (Solicitor General, Dept. of Labor) to the President regarding Public Resolution 44 (Executive Order creating the NLRB); from Campbell MacCulloch to Beatrice M. Stern (Assistant Executive Secretary, NLRB) about the status of regional labor boards; Mr. Eliot's (Office of the Solictor, Dept. of Labor) description of the U.S. Conciliation Service; from Donald Richberg (Executive Director, National Emergency Council) to the Chairman in regard to the duplication of efforts by groups representing the Government in the Baltimore trucking strike; 2 charts entitled "National Industrial Relations Boards and Labor Boards and National Complaints Committees," and "Boards Known to be in the Process of Organization;" Lloyd K. Garrison's (Chairman. NLRB) inquiry into personal relations and operations of regional labor boards, with attention to boards' relationship with the conciliation service; copy of "Suggested Bookeeping Arrangements Between the Dept. of Labor and the NLRB".
      - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 28)
        7/17/34-7/31/34; MacCulloch's description of his regional board and discussion of jurisdiction; William Leiserson's interview regarding the Petroleum Administration and the Petroleum Board; memo on existing industrial boards; list of industrial relations or labor boards and complaint committees; autobiographical letter from Nathan Witt to Charles Wyzanski explaining his interest in law and American labor history; from Max A. Egloff for the files on Republic and Apollo Steel, wage contracts; letter of recommendation from Bethuel N (M.) Webster, Jr. to Garrison for Nathan Witt; Paul Herzog's summary of the Houde Engineering case; from Garrison to the Executive Director National Emergency Council regarding the handling of the Baltimore trucking strike; Estelle Frankfurter's discussion of the Guide Lamp case and majority rule; Ralph A. Lind's (Regional Director, Cleveland Regional Labor Board) discussion of a bi-partisan board problems.
      - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        8/3/34-8/30/34; Letter from Garrison to Busfield concerning authority to order elections and Section 7a violations; from Frank Coffee (Regional Director, Atlanta Regional Labor Board) to Garrison on the textile labor situation in the South, includes a state by state description focusing on Communism (6pp); from Millis to John M. Carmody (National Mediation Board) discussing candidates for positions as regional directors; from Millis and Edwin S. Smith (Executive Board Member. NLRB) to Frances Perkins discussing Garrison's resignation; from Garrison to Hugh L. Kerwin (Director of Conciliation) outlining a proposed working arrangement between the Dept. of Labor and the NLRB; from Benedict Wolf to Alice M. Rossiter regarding regional boards, reorganization, standardization of procedure and jurisdiction; from the Dept. of Justice to William G. Rice Jr. (General Counsel, NLRB) about the A. Roth and Co. case; from William Rice Jr. to Professor Wilber Katz regarding the S. Dresner and Son case; from the President to Glenn Frank (President, University of Wisconsin) asking if Garrison can have leave from his University obligations to continue work with the NLRB; from Harry Millis to Ralph Lind on organizational structure; to Dr. Edwin A. Elliott (The Compliance Board, Houston) inviting him to become Director of the Texas Oklahoma Board; Millis' discussion regional board problems; from R. Gordon Wagenet (Director, Region 16) to Millis in regard to his trip to Pittsburgh, contains synopsis of interviews with various people for different jobs; to Frank X. Martel (President, Detroit Federation of Labor) requesting a reference for Father Seidenberg for the position of Regional Director in Detroit; from Glenn Frank to the President expressing the University's need for Garrison and stating that if he decides to stay with the NLRB he will have to give up his deanship.
      - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 30)
        9/1/34-9/18/34; Letters from Lloyd Garrison to the President relating to the textile strike, and recommending the creation of a special board under Public Resolution 44; from William Green (President, American Federation of Labor (A.F.of L.) to Garrison congratulating the Board on their decision in the Houde Engineering case; Estelle Frankfurter's summary of interviews with Code Authorities' Complaints Committees; from Herber Blankenhorn (NLRB, Research) to the Board on the necessity for centralized investigation and research; from Lind to Millis about the creation of a Northern-Ohio-Michigan Labor Relations Board; from Millis to Kent S. Clow (James B. Clow & Sons) concerning the selection of regional directors; letter from Hugh S. Johnson (Administrator, NRA) to Houde Engineering Corp. informing them that they violated Sec. 7a of the NIRA; significant memo from Dorothy A. Moncure (Assistant Counsel, Compliance Division) to A.T. Martin (Associate Counsel, Compliance Division) about Houde Engineering Corp., and recommending the removal of the Blue Eagle, includes a 4 page fact finding record; from George W. Taylor (NRA) to Garrison reporting low morale among Philadelphia members; Millis'discussion of who should serve as chairman at hearings.
      - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 31)
        9/19/34-9/29/34; From Edwin S. Smith to Blackwell Smith (Assistant Administrator for Policy, NRA) concerning industrial boards; from Millis to Dr. Earl R. Beckner (Indianapolis Regional Labor Board) concerning the discharge of Mr. Watson (Executive Secretary, Indiana Regional Labor Board); from Garrison to the President on the impending Seamens' Strike on the Atlantic Coast and the Gulf, and previewing Board action as well as securing government support; from Major Root to Garrison concerning low morale among the Philadelphia Regional Labor Board members; from the President to Garrison approving the Boards' plan of action in the Seamen's strike; the file on the Houde Engineering case providing background and compliance history (7pp); Towne J. Nylander's (Assistant Secretary, Los Angeles Regional Labor Board) discussion of industrial board members' resignations; from Millis to Garrison about George Pratt of Kansas City, MO, assessing his education, political persuasion and experience in regard to working with the Kansas City Regional Labor Board.
      - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 32)
        10/2/34-10/30/34; Memo from Edwin S. Smith to Garrison and Millis, includes a questionaire to be sent to industrial boards; from Robert E. Watts (General Counsel, NLRB) to the Attorney General submitting the Houde Case for review; memo regarding the status of strikers as employees, includes information relevant to Houde case; memo on public reaction to the Houde decision (majority rule in collective bargaining); from T.F.E. (?) to the Board about the Detroit Street Railway case; from Harry Millis to Roy C. Jacobson (Director, Denver Regional Board) concerning pay of panel members; from Stephen Early (Assistant Secretary to the President) to Garrison confirming the President's acceptance of his resignation; from Millis to Garrison (Dean, The Law School, University of Wisconsin) about offering Scrinshaw the Associate Directorship of the Milwaukee office; from Elisha Hanson (Attorney for the San Francisco Call-Bulletin) to Edwin S. Smith opposing NLRB jurisdiction in the Jennings controversy, and recommemding the case be turned over to the Newspaper Industrial Board; from Harold M. Stephens (Assistant Attorney General) to Robert Watts (Special Counsel, NLRB) on Houde Engineering case,(enclosure no. 381814 unattached); from Stanley Mathewson (Director, Cincinnati Regional Labor Board) to Benedict Wolf about the American Rolling Mill Co.
      - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 33)